Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Weeksville Heritage Center, 2017; 2016.027.3
  - Brown Green, Myrah, 2017 February 7; 2016.027.3.03
    In this interview, Myrah Brown Green recalls many of her biographical highlights. She remembers her youth in a neighborhood of Cambridge, Massachusetts, where she experienced racism from a childhood friend's father and a stutter which she believes had developed from a fear of needles. She remembers meeting Richard Green for the first time and realizing his impact on the community in Brooklyn. Brown Green discusses starting the Crown Heights Youth Collective, the difficulty in maintaining the organization, and the roles that she and her husband played during the social upheaval in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in August of 1991. She also references the Summer Youth Employment Program that she directed to specifically support pregnant teenage women. Brown Green relates her involvement in starting up a home school. In closing she shares where her focus is in 2017; taking part in raising a granddaughter, publishing a book, and exhibiting her quilted artwork. Her husband, Richard Green, was recorded for Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn History Society and the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020). Interview conducted by Larry Weekes.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Massachusetts; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brown Green, Myrah; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Crown Heights Collective Fellowship and Peace Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Youth Collective (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Richard; Pratt Institute; St. Francis College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Derico, Jean with Butler, Herman, 2017 January 6; 2016.027.3.04
    Aged sixty-three at time of the 2017 interview, Jean Derico is a Black second grade teacher who was born in the Bronx and lived most of her life in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She attended Hunter College in the early 1970s and received her master's degree in education at Adelphi University soon afterwards. Derico began teaching at the Weeksville School (PS 243) in 1984-1985 and has been at the school ever since. Aged eighty-three at the time of the interview, Herman Butler is a school janitor/fireman who has been working at the Weeksville School since 1967. He is originally from Augusta, Georgia.
    In this interview, Jean Derico talks about her experience as an educator at PS 243 and how the school changed during her three decades-long teaching career. She describes how the school initially was a very prominent one; with her being part of a change in demographics in regard to the teachers employed. Derico evaluates how the student population started to decrease with the rise of charter schools. She also discusses the changes in demographics both racially and generationally that she has witnessed in her profession. She also shares about the Weeksville museum that was at the school; how it was turned into a junk room and how it was eventually re-opened in 2015 through the impetus of the local Parent Teacher Association president's (Donnaly Lamont) proactivity. Herman Butler intermittently adds description of his experience at PS 243; recalling the school's participation in the archeological dig that occurred in 1968 and when the school changed its name from the Isaac Newton School to the Weeksville School. He also discusses how the school has changed since 1967 and how it may have lost the "feeling of the community." Interview conducted by Obden Mondésir.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Charter schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Exhibitions; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Butler, Herman; Derico, Jean L.; Markowitz, Marty; P.S. 243 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Leach-James, Linda Patricia, 2017 January 12; 2016.027.3.05
    Linda Patricia Leach-James was born and raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her parents, Walter C. Leach and Rosalind Boston (nee Leach), also raised a younger brother and sister. Leach-James attended St. Gregory the Great Elementary School and graduated from Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School in 1968. She went on to an undergraduate degree at Hampton Institute in Virginia. After marrying, starting a family, and taking the family abroad to France, she raised her children in France from the early 1980s to early 1990s. She then returned with her family to live full-time in Crown Heights. Leach-James took her father's previously-held position as a co-owner in the local storefront insurance brokerage firm, Cambridge and Leach. She is also a grandmother.
    In the interview, Linda Patricia Leach-James speaks about her experiences in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn as a member of a middle class African American family. She discusses her upbringing and her educational experiences in Catholic parochial schools. Leach-James recalls key biographical turning points. She remembers arriving to college and attending Hampton Institute, a historically Black school. Leach-James references her time living in a few towns in France. She reflects on how her family reacted and coped during the August, 1991 event that's sometimes known as the Crown Heights riot. Interview conducted by Vivian Millicent Warfield.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Church schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; France; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Virginia; Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School for Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Public Library; Erasmus Hall High School; Hampton Institute; Leach-James, Linda Patricia; Saint Gregory's Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Maxwell, Richard, 2017 February 17; 2016.027.3.06
    Biographic note
    Richard Maxwell was born to an African-American family in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in 1944. Shortly thereafter, the family moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. In adulthood, Maxwell moved to the Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn, having come to know the adjacent Crown Heights neighborhood quite well. In the mid-1960s, Maxwell served a tour of duty in the army before the Vietnam conflict escalated. He received master's degrees from Brooklyn College and City College. He has worked in education in Brooklyn since the 1970s. Maxwell held multiple positions during his career as an educator; perhaps most notably as a school guidance counselor in District 75.
    In the interview, Richard Maxwell initially discusses the changing boundaries of central Brooklyn and the demographic and political influences that create them. He also focuses on encountering the Jewish community in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn during the 1940s and how he grew up— predominantly on Jefferson Street and Nostrand Avenue. He recalls the many positions that he held in the Department of Education and his interactions with Brooklyn political players. He mentions his time as a student at Boys' High School, its preponderance of quality basketball players, and how that played a role in his social life growing up. Maxwell reflects on his decision to move closer to his brother— who, after serving in Vietnam, suffered from the effects of Agent Orange— which led him to work at the notoriously difficult school IS 320. He speculates on the issues of school safety and the gang behavior that he encountered as an anti-gang specialist and acknowledges the patterns among some youths that impacted the August 1991 uprising in Crown Heights. Maxwell identifies Richard Green as an educator who helped quell the uproar and violence that occurred at that time. In closing, he lists many of the bars that he frequented in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Brigitte Winston.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Children's Museum; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Board of Education; Community School District 17 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community School District 75 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Youth Collective (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Richard; Maxwell, Richard John; P.S. 375 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Naison, Mark, 2017 January 4; 2016.027.3.07
    Born in Brooklyn in 1946, Dr. Mark Naison was seventy years old at the time of the 2017 interview. Raised in a Jewish family household where reading was emphasized, he attended PS 91, Winthrop Junior High School, and Wingate High School. Naison's pugilism led to a transfer to Erasmus High. He went on to Columbia University and a professorship of History at Fordham University.
    In this interview, Dr. Mark Naison talks about life in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn during the 1950s. He describes the neighborhood as very working class and, in demographic terms, mostly Italian and Jewish. Dr. Naison remembers being ostracized for the intellectual pursuits that his parents foisted upon him, and the gameplay, athletics, and fighting with his public school peers which he used as social compensation. Interview conducted by Obden Mondésir.
    Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social classes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Congress of Racial Equality. Brooklyn Chapter; Erasmus Hall High School; George W. Wingate High School; Naison, Mark D., 1946-; P.S. 91 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Produced media, 2017; 2016.027.1.4
  Open to users without restriction. Please consult library staff for further more details and assistance.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Recordings are born-digital.
  The series contains recordings of six of the seven public programs organized by Brooklyn Historical Society, Weeksville Heritage Center, and Brooklyn Movement Center in relation to the Voices of Crown Heights oral history project conducted by Zaheer Ali, Oral Historian, and Amaka Okechukwu, Project Coordinator, from 2016 to 2017. The programs covered topics of importance to the community including gentrification, race relations, education, policing, and community safety. Programs included panel discussions with a moderator including a question and answer session with the audience, as well as facilitated listening sessions of curated excerpts of oral histories. The programs were edited following recording for a production-quality recording for broadcast.
  List of Programs:
  March 11, 2017, Community Classroom: Ideas, Innovation, and Education Equity
  Hosted by Weeksville Heritage Center in Crown Heights
  Participants:Christopher Battist (IntegrateNYC4Me), Petrushka Bazin Larsen (Brooklyn Children's Museum), Max Freedman (Aritst and Educator), Stanley Kinard (Carter G. Woodson Cultural Literacy Project and the Brownsville Heritage House)
  April 24, 2017, Story of Policing in Crown Heights—Community Listening Session
  Hosted by Brooklyn Movement Center at Repair the World in Crown Heights
  Participants: Mark Winston Griffith (Brooklyn Movement Center), Walis Johnson (Brooklyn Movement Center)
  May 16, 2017, Beyond Police: Bringing Public Safety to Crown Heights
  Hosted by Brooklyn Movement Center, Center for Law and Social Justice at Medgar Evers College, at Brooklyn Children's Museum in Crown Heights
  Participants: Ashleigh Eubanks (Audre Lorde Project's Safe Outside the System), Mark Winston Griffith (Brooklyn Movement Center), Shalawn Langhorne (Community Board 8), Marlon Peterson (Crown Heights SOS), Anthonine Pierre (Crown Heights Cop Watch)
  June 12, 2017, Listening Session and Discussion: Stories of Neighborhood Change
  Hosted by Brooklyn Historical Society
  Participants: Zaheer Ali (Brooklyn Historical Society), Amaka Okechukwu (Brooklyn Historical Society)
  July 18, 2017, The New Crown Heights? A Neighborhood and Its Future
  Participants: Amy Ellenbogen (Crown Heights Mediation Center), Mordechai Lightstone (Chabad.org), Lisa Mathis (Crown Heights Tenants Union), Joy-Ann Reid (MSNBC), Sharon Wedderburn (Community Board 8), Michael de Zayas (Entrepreneur/Business Owner)